<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>How To Play Guitar</title>
    <description>I taught myself to play guitar. You can too. </description>
    <link>http://howtoplayguitar.xyz/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://howtoplayguitar.xyz/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Practice Tips</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;play-slowly&quot;&gt;Play slowly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve heard it 14,000 times today already, but I’m going to say it again: slow down. Play like you are underwater. Give your hands some time to get into place before you try to sound the notes. Tension is the enemy on a guitar, and you won’t be able to play quickly at first without getting very tense.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;play-equally&quot;&gt;Play Equally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throw on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.metronomeonline.com/&quot;&gt;metronome&lt;/a&gt; and start grooving with it. You might hate this at first, but you’re going to have to get used to the whole idea of playing to a click if you’re ever going record anything, or play with anyone else, or sound good. You need some kind of click, either out loud, or in your head, that you’re grooving with. That’s what makes your playing sound professional. Well that and a few other things. But professional musicians have a keen ear for time, and I think you should start playing around with &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; from the beginning. A metronomic click gives you a lot of feedback about the timing of your playing, so you can more clearly hear how you are &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; phrasing your notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;think-long-term&quot;&gt;Think long term&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you keep playing, you will gradually get better and better. It’s hard to transform your playing overnight, but over time you’ll conquer any obstacles in your way as long as you keep playing. You don’t have to play for hours every day, just 15 minutes a day will get your fingers thinking about the guitar, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://trainingthemusicalbrain.blogspot.ca/2011/10/sleep-and-memory-consolidation.html&quot;&gt;your playing will improve over night. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;play-in-little-mini-loops&quot;&gt;Play in little mini loops&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I can’t quite get a phrase down, or a chord change, the way I get past it is by just playing the same phrase slowly, over and over again. It sounds obvious, and it is, frankly. But it does the job for me. Don’t worry about playing the whole thing through from start to finish, unless you are obsessed with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ftlgame.com/&quot;&gt;FTL.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learn-to-play-some-blues&quot;&gt;Learn to play some blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you can barely play the guitar at all, you can play a blues song. Well you can create your own unique version anyway. That’s a feat in itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-it-fun&quot;&gt;Keep it fun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more fun you have when you play, the more expressive a player you will become.  Play with other people as soon as you can, it is &lt;em&gt;alot&lt;/em&gt; of fun, and probably unlike anything you’ve ever done before. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;listen-to-the-greats&quot;&gt;Listen to the greats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sit back and listen to your favourite guitar solo, imagining how it was played to get that sound. Imagine playing like that yourself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stay-in-tune&quot;&gt;Stay in tune&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tune your guitar easily with GuitarTuna &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/ie/app/guitar-tuna-ultimate-free/id527588389?mt=8&quot;&gt;iPhone&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.ovelin.guitartuna&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;Android&lt;/a&gt; for your smartphone.
There are loads of other tuners available there, but I’m quite fond of Guitar Tuna, it seems slighly less buggy than the others, and you’ve gotta love that graph it has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://a3.mzstatic.com/eu/r30/Purple5/v4/7b/8b/dc/7b8bdc3c-7b94-30ce-4f2a-2925150e722d/screen568x568.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Guitar Tuna Graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has a metronome built in too, which is pretty handy. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://howtoplayguitar.xyz/practice-tips</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://howtoplayguitar.xyz/practice-tips</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
